Guide to the Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection. 1960-1978
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection
1960-1978
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A0382
Farnsworth, Elma
The Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection contains 45 compact discs.
The Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection (1960-1978) contains audio recordings of Farnsworth speaking to audiences as well as recordings his wife, Elma G. "Pem" Farnsworth, made while researching a biography following his death in 1971. Philo Taylor Farnsworth (1906-1971) was a researcher, writer, and a pioneering developer of television, radar technology, peacetime applications of nuclear fusion, and the infant incubator.
Biographical Note
Philo Taylor Farnsworth (1906-1971) was born on 19 August 1906, to Lewis Edwin and Serena Bastian Farnsworth in a log cabin at Indian Creek, near the town of Beaver in Southwestern Utah. He was the namesake of his paternal grandfather who built the log home in 1856 while settling the area at the request of Mormon Church leader Brigham Young.
Philo was six years old when the hand-cranked Bell telephone and Edison gramophone became well known, just old enough to become inquisitive about motors, magnets, coils, armatures, and other components of the newly popular electric power. By the time his family moved to his Uncle Albert's 240 acre ranch near Rigby, Idaho the thirteen-year-old was reading everything about electricity that he could get his hands on, including instructions to the farm's Delco power system. However, Philo's avid reading of Popular Science and other technical magazines found in the attic, soon had him using the power system to operate the family's washing machine, sewing machine, and barn lights.
Philo's appetite for knowledge gave him a mental grasp of such developing concepts as Einstein's theory of relativity, sub-atomic particles, radio waves, and mechanic disc-operated television. He was also well ahead of his classmates in most math and science subjects by the time he entered Rigby High School. In fact, it was in his first chemistry class that he disclosed his idea of an "image dissector tube." Such a vacuum tube, he suggested, was capable of operating a television unit electronically by shooting a stream of electrons toward a fluorescent screen, thereby accurately reflecting pre-designated images.
With the loss of his uncle's farm in 1922, Philo's family moved to Provo, Utah. For the next two years, Philo attended Brigham Young University. It was there that he was introduced to Elma "Pem" Gardner in 1924. However, just three months later, he was forced to leave school to assume the role of family provider when his father died.
Farnsworth's attempts to provide support for himself and his family were many and varied during this period. He labored on logging crews, repaired and delivered radios, sold electrical products door to door, and worked on the railroad as an electrician. His acumen in math and science helped him pass the Navy's Officer Candidate School Examination, but after being assigned to Annapolis as a first-year midshipman he decided a military career was not his goal. He returned home to work on a Salt Lake City street cleaning crew. It was his knowledge of Salt Lake City's street plan that eventually earned him a supervisor position for an out-of-state charitable organization managed by George Everson and Leslie Gorrell.
Everson and Gorrell were professional fundraisers from California who were impressed with Farnsworth's ability to organize a job, dedicate himself to completing the tasks involved, and motivate other team members, They listened to him recount his ideas of electronic television as they performed the mundane work of folding, stuffing, sorting, and stamping bulk mailings of fundraising letters, and became convinced of the investment possibilities such a venture could bring. So impressed were these two men with Farnsworth's knowledge of current television literature and his own innovative concepts, they offered to financially support the venture under a formal partnership know as Everson, Farnsworth & Gorrell. Three days later, on 27 May 1926, Philo and Pem were married.
On 7 September 1927, George Everson watched with staff members as Farnsworth slowly turned on the controls. An unmistakable line appeared across the small bluish square of light on the end of the Oscillite tube. Although fuzzy at first, it became distinct with adjustment, and through the visual static each could see the side of a black triangle previously inserted by Pem's brother, Cliff Gardner.
For the next three years support was provided by a group of bankers and investors calling themselves Crocker Research Laboratories. In March 1929, Jesse McCarger took the reins of the fledgling group, provided substantially more support and renamed the company Television, Inc. It was during this period (1929-1933), that publicity catapulted the promise of this little organization. However, with public awareness came the problems of competition, races to the patent office and legal disputes. The most significant and long-lasting conflict began in April 1930, when Dr. Vladimir Zworykin of Westinghouse visited Farnsworth's Laboratory. For three days he was a guest of the investors, who hoped to persuade Zworykin's employer to purchase their small company. But, unbeknownst to the Farnsworth staff, Zworykin had recently been hired by RCA, who sent him to the laboratory to obtain information for replicating the necessary television equipment. For the next decade Farnsworth and his attorneys were involved in court battles endeavoring to convince the United States Patent Office that it was he and not Vladimir Zworykin who had invented the basic components of electronic television. It was later to be one of Farnsworth's great professional satisfactions to have rival competitor RCA concede and pay one million dollars for rights to the Farnsworth patents.
During 1933, Farnsworth acquired enough investment capital to restructure the organization and change its name to Farnsworth Television, Inc. This name remained until 1938, when management purchased the Capehart Company of Fort Wayne along with a general household utilities plant in Marion, Indiana. With these acquisitions they were prepared to compete in the blossoming radio and phonograph manufacturing market. But while endeavoring to develop and refine his electronic television invention, Farnsworth was also responsible for providing investors with saleable products during the post-depression economy and directing and supervising laboratory personnel.
With the slowdown in radio and television production during the war years, Farnsworth closed down his Fort Wayne, Indiana home and moved permanently to Fernworth Farm in Brownfield, Maine. The Farnsworth Company had been converted to the production of war materials and was supplying electronic components to the federal government. With a subsidy from the Farnsworth Company, Farnsworth was able to spend more time developing ideas that had previously been dwarfed by the race for television patents. From 1939-1948 he utilized the farms lumber resources for the production of ammunition boxes for the War Production Board. The family venture was organized under the name of Farnsworth Wood Products Company and flourished for the duration of the war.
Anticipating the end of the war, RCA, Philco, and several other large companies received their commercial licenses from the FCC. They immediately began retooling their equipment for the commercial manufacturing of televisions. The Farnsworth Company quickly found itself at the rear of this aggressive pack of electronics firms in the scramble for parts and materials. In addition, the one-year grace period allowed by the federal government for repayment of its wartime bank loans was up. The company found itself financially strapped and frantically tried to sell its assets in order to remain afloat in the post-war market. When all but the original plant had been sold, substantial bank loans still remained outstanding. The board of directors voted to sell the company to International Telephone and Telegraph (ITT) in 1949. Under the new management, Farnsworth retained his position as vice president of research and advance engineering. His primary function within the ITT system was to engineer his staff toward timely completion of space-age contracts awarded by the Air Force and other government agencies. During the next eighteen years he was to make ITT his home. It was within this environment that he invented components of the Defense Early Warning Signal, the PPI Projector (which allowed safe control of air traffic from the ground), an infrared telescope, submarine detection devices, radar calibration equipment, and other inventions.
Although his health continued to deteriorate, he actively worked on many military research projects. Nevertheless, due to illness and the time necessary for recuperation, ITT transferred him from his responsibilities as vice president of research to that of systems consultant. As such, he was able to follow his own pursuits and still remain on the ITT payroll. Fortunately, ITT management agreed to nominally fund his new controlled fusion ideas. He and staff members invented and refined a series of fusion reaction tubes called "fusors." Publicity about his activities persuaded ITT management to raise Farnsworth's salary and promote him to the position of director of research. For Scientific reasons unknown to Farnsworth and his staff, the necessary reaction lasted no longer than thirty seconds. In December 1965, ITT came under pressure from its board of directors to terminate the expensive fusion research and sell the Farnsworth subsidiary. It was only from the urging of President Harold Geneen that the 1966 budget was accepted, permitting ITT's fusion research one additional year. However, the stress associated with this managerial ultimatum threw Farnsworth into relapse. One year later he was terminated and eventually allowed medical retirement.
In the spring off 1967, Farnsworth and his family moved back to Utah to continue his fusion research at Brigham Young University, which presented him with an honorary doctorate. The university also offered him office space and an underground concrete bunker location for the project realizing the fusion lab was to be dismantled at ITT, Farnsworth invited staff members to accompany him to Salt Lake City as team members in his planned Philo T. Farnsworth Associates (PTFA) organization. By late 1968 the associates began holding regular business meetings and PTFA was underway. However, although a contract with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration was promptly secured and more possibilities were within reach, the financing needed to pay the $24,000 in monthly expenses for equipment rental and salaries was stalled.
By Christmas 1970, PTFA had failed to secure the necessary financing, the Farnsworth's had sold all their own ITT stock and cashed out Philo's life insurance policy to maintain organization stability. The underwriter had failed to provide the financial backing that was to have supported the organization during its critical first year. The banks called-in all outstanding loans. Repossession notices were placed on anything not previously sold and the Internal Revenue Service put a lock on the laboratory door until delinquent taxes were paid. During January 1970, Philo T. Farnsworth Associates disbanded. Farnsworth became seriously ill with pneumonia and died on 11 March 1971.
Although best known for his development of television, Farnsworth was involved in research in many other areas. He invented the first infant incubator. He was involved in the development of radar, peacetime uses of atomic energy, and the nuclear fusion process. At his death, Farnsworth held 300 U.S. and foreign patents, and Scientific American magazine called him one of the ten greatest mathematicians of his time.
Elma "Pem" Gardner Farnsworth (1908- 2006) was born on 25 February 1908 in Jensen, Utah. "Pem", as she was affectionately known, married Philo Taylor Farnsworth in 1926. She became part of her husband's lab team, handling the technical drawings for his early experiments on his vision for television and was present in San Francisco on 7 September 1927, when electronic television was first demonstrated successfully. Pem Farnsworth was the first person ever to appear on a cathode-ray-tube receiver via transmission from her husband's lab and has been referred to as "The Mother of Television."
During the last three decades following Philo's death, Elma Farnsworth had been a tireless advocate of her husband's work. During this period he received many posthumous honors. In 1977 he was awarded an Emmy by the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences; in 1983 his image was placed on a U.S. postage stamp; the Inventors Hall of Fame inducted him as a member in 1984. In 1990 a life-sized statue of him was placed in the Statuary Hall in Washington D.C. Elma wrote a biography on Philo It was published in 1989 with the title Distant Vision: Romance and Discovery on an Invisible Frontier.
Well into her 90's Mrs. Farnsworth continued her cause and was successful in lobbying the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences to consider creating an award in honor of her husband's accomplishments. She took center stage to present the first " Philo T. Farnsworth" award for technical excellence in television at the 56th Annual Emmy Awards in Los Angeles in 2003. A devout Mormon, she derived her greatest satisfaction from meeting school children and encouraging them to follow in her late husband's footsteps. Elma died on 27 April 2006 at the age of 98
The Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth audio collection (1960-1978) contains audio recordings of Farnsworth speaking to audiences as well as recordings his wife, Elma G. "Pem" Farnsworth, made while researching a biography following his death in 1971. The recordings mostly contain Philo's wife, Pem, and people that knew Farnsworth and worked with him. On each disc she asks them questions and they respond and both tell stories that provide a glimpse of the life of Philo Farnsworth. The collection is digitized and available to listen to on compact disc.
The materials are arranged chronologically.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Philo T. and Elma G. Farnsworth papers (Ms 648).
Utah; Television--History; Nuclear fusion; Technology; Sound Recordings; Oral Histories; Sound recordings
- 1960, Compact disc (Disc 1)
  - "PTF Talk at Manchester College" Fall 1960 Side 1 (Track 1)
    Philo and his wife went from Hollywood to San Francisco, and the Crocker Bank agreed to put up $25000 in addition to the $8000 dollars they had already invested.
    His brother in law worked as his lab assistant.
    They were able to find a scientist from Cal who could blow the glass tube they needed.
    Philo says that it took approximately six months to get the lab set up.
    After eighteen months, he says that they could see a distinguishable picture on the screen.
    Early on, there was no competition and the competition that came to exist wasn't necessarily designed in the same way and didn't work as well.
    In 1932 the first commercial message sent using his tube by the Institute of Radio Engineers in San Francisco.
    Many people began to visit as it became more and more clear that his version of the television would actually work.
    They applied for 35 patents the first year, and again about that many the second year.
    He built the first electron microscope in 1927, and then a field emission ion microscope.
    By 1932 Philo felt that the picture quality was pretty good. He felt that the television helped to pull the United States out of the great depression, as did Dr. Tethering of General Motors.
    In 1934 he went to the Franklin Institute to demonstrate the television, which was a 15 inch tube. 500 people at a time came to watch the demonstration and this continued from 11 am to 11 pm each day every twenty minutes for three weeks.
    They were going to sell an interest to United Artists, but when they were going to demonstrate the capabilities of the television it didn't work very well. They managed to fix it, but the deal fell through when the attorney in charge of the deal was found to be taking bribes.
    By 1934 Philco and the American Telephone Telegraph Company as well as a German and British company were licensed to use his technology. He then discusses how the technology actually works. He holds 165 American patents and 140 foreign patents.
    He talks about the implications of national and international television and its possible impact on the world. He also discusses the changing technology in color, number of stations, etc.
    He launches into a longer dialogue about Russia, home improvements, bomb shelters, and more.
  - "PTF Talk at Manchester College" Fall 1960 Side 2 (Track 2)
    Begins to talk about cancers, how he believes they come about, and how believes they could be treated or even cured.
    He begins to demonstrate an electronic device of some kind, talk is relatively technical and difficult to comprehend without the visual part of the presentation.
    He also describes his ideas for space travel and his expectations for its growth over the next twenty years.
    He believes that energy will be able to be produced limitlessly and free in the near future and that people will be able to purchase cars and spaceships with unlimited energy supplies built into them during the late 1960s.
    He discusses how to make yourself a more creative and innovative person.
- March 1962, Compact disc (Disc 2)
  - "Philo Farnsworth before the Art Convention of Indianapolis, Ind." 3/23/62, 1962 (Track 2)
    Introductory speaker talks about Farnsworth's work with television as well as radioactive materials.
    Philo Farnsworth talks about population and how it will grow wildly in the early 2000s.
    Time is a perspective, it has no physical significance, he believes that space is non-existent (?). He believes that mileage in space will work very differently as we get past Pluto because there will essentially be zero mass in the space.
    He believes by the end of the decade speeds in space will reach up to 1000 miles per second.
    Farnsworth says that if you live during the next ten years you will likely live 100 years, and if you live during the following ten years, you will likely live 1000 in terms of relative years. A little unsure exactly what he is saying here, but I believe he is talking about the rapid growth of technology in an exponential fashion meaning that life will not actually last longer, but that people will experience relatively 'more'.
    Talks about his predictions for space exploration and his expectation that anyone will be able to visit Mars by 1970.
    Farnsworth talks about fusion energy and how he believes it will change our life experience – individual energy sources with enough fuel for a lifetime for a small cost.
    Talks about energy costs and what he believes will be their drastic reduction in price. Talks about heating the whole of New York City for less than a dollar.
    He talks about the building of space colonies to solve what he believes is an inevitable population overgrowth.
    Farnsworth discusses the building of bomb shelters as a civic project as opposed to a government sponsored one.
    His wife tells the story of his attempt to develop a fusion device.
  - "What to expect of our future" - PTF speech to Indianapolis, Ind. State art groups 3/23/62, 1962 (Track 3)
    Secondary recording of the same speech as #2.
- March 1962, 1968, Compact disc (Disc 3)
  - "What to expect of our future – PTF speech to Indianapolis, Ind. State art groups" 3/23/62, 1962 (Track 3)
    Second half of the second recording of same speech as #2.
  - "Beginning at 80" Side 1, Los Altos, 1968 (Track 4)
    Man and woman tell a story about driving on the highway, the sound quality is very poor and it is difficult to hear exactly what they are saying.
    There is music playing on a separate track maybe? It doesn't seem to be in the background because the words of the speakers are so distorted and the music is very clear and it drowns out what the people are saying.
    It's not loud, but it makes their speech totally unintelligible. You can hear occasional words but huge parts of the sentence are lost. The words are very muddy.
    This continues for the entire track.
- 1968, Compact disc (Disc 4)
  - "Meeting at 80" Phil, Cliff, Pem, Seline Los Altos 1968 (Track 4)
    Once again, sound quality is very poor.
    Very hard to follow conversation, I believe four of them are talking but they often talk over each other and that combined with the poor sound quality makes it very jumbled.
    The sound cuts out and back in, it now seems to be a slightly different conversation but once again the number of people talking makes it difficult to follow.
    It is a meeting discussing the seal (?) for an unnamed company, as well as the differences from a trademark.
    They discuss selling 1,050,000 shares of a company at a price of $12/share.
    The primary man who is talking describes a phone conversation with the police in which they ask him to provide them with tubes capable of recording infrared images. They want to use it over binoculars to help get evidence against drug smugglers.
    They say that they may or may not be able to handle the increase in business and consider passing it off to a competitor, then get to talking about the specs for the product and what the police force currently has. This discussion seems to relate especially to what the medium for recording will actually be.
    The Speaker talks about his personal desire to stop drug trafficking as his main motivation as opposed to profit.
    They debate whether or not to pair with ITT (?), who is their competitor, to work on this project and are divided to some extent.
    A lady asks if she can have 25 shares of stock per month which she says are valued at approximately $200 in total. The meeting is a board of director's meeting.
    They talk about getting bids from insurance companies, but it's not entirely clear what they are interested in having insured.
    They discuss whether taking on another project will overextend them, and then discuss which projects they should be focusing on primarily based on quickest return. They are considering doing something with a dryer, but as of yet it hasn't been chosen for sure.
    The man in charge discusses whether or not he can hire a secretary who will work for nine months of the year while pursuing her CPA for the other three.
    They don't want to hire someone because of her inability to be quiet, as they fear that she will talk about projects that she is not allowed to outside of work.
  - "Copy of tape made at Cliff's home. Phil, Pem, Seline, Bo, Cliff" 1968 (Track 5)
    A woman introduces the segment saying that she will play a tape that was recorded in 1968.
    Talking is quite muddled once again. Some of the speakers are somewhat understandable, but others are not enunciating clearly and it is nearly impossible to keep track of the conversation given that only about half of what is said can be heard.